Catherine Wistar Bache Papers 1788-1822 Mss.B.B124
American Philosophical Society
Catharine Wistar Bache Papers
1788-1822
Mss.B.B124
American Philosophical Society
0.25 Linear feet
Catherine Wistar Bache (1805-1886) was the point of connection between two of Philadelphia's most illustrious families of the late eighteenth century. Daughter of the physician Caspar Wistar, in November 1797 she married Dr. William Bache, who was the son of Richard Bache and the grandson of Benjamin Franklin. Primarily letters to Mrs. Bache (wife of Dr. William Bache) of Philadelphia, from Mrs. David Hosack (nee Mary Eddy), Mrs. Elizabeth Trist, and Mary Jones. The letters are personal and concern family life, activities of husbands, etc., with many references to Caspar Wistar, There are comments on diseases, education (at William and Mary College), war, and politics. References are also made to the deaths of Richard Bache and Caspar Wistar, and to Benjamin Franklin's Stockado (a musical instrument).
Bache, Catherine Wistar, 1770-1820
Early American History Note
This relatively small collection contains rich correspondence often directed to Catherine Wistar Bache, the daughter of prominent doctor Caspar Wistar and wife of Richard Bache’s son. The collection is one of the many to the Bache-Franklin collections at the APS. This specific collection contains numerous letters from other women, often wives and mothers, to Catherine. There are a few letters to Caspar Wistar and William Bache (Catherine’s husband), which often discuss current events, specifically Anthony Wayne’s victory at Fallen Timbers in 1794 and the Whiskey Rebellion. The letters to Catherine discuss current affairs, such as the Yellow Fever epidemic and the War of 1812. More often, however, the letters relate family and personal matters. The letters primarily discuss husbands, family activities, children, and other such topics. Some of the early letters also touch upon gender relations and courtship. For instance, a male correspondent wrote Catherine that he has not received any letters from his “female correspondents” and was thus hoping “to renew the friendly intercourse,” and Mary Eddy discussed flirtations. The correspondence in this collection spans more than thirty years, and therefore also provides insight on the changing concerns of Catherine as a young single woman, wife, and mother. William Bache was sent to Louisiana in 1803 in an official post overseeing a hospital. Discussion of moving to Louisiana is included in the collection, during which references to “Captain Lewis” are made, likely Meriwether Lewis. Because of her position in society, these letters often provide portraits and anecdotes of prominent figures.
Related Archival Materials note
At the APS, see also the numerous collections related to Benjamin Franklin and to various members of the Bache family. The Department of Rare Books and Manuscripts at Princeton University houses a collection of Bache and Wistar Family Correspondence (call no. C0381).
The APS also houses the papers of Sarah Bache Hodge, daughter of Catherine and William Bache.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Acquired from Marian Carson, 1967.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of Catharine Wistar Bache consist of 114 letters written by and to Catharine Wistar Bache, wife of Dr. William Bache of Philadelphia. Bache's major correspondents include Mary Eddy Hosack (wife of the physician David Hosack), Elizabeth Trist, and Mary Trist Jones. Primarily personal in nature, these letters discuss family and husbands, and contain numerous references to Catharine's father, Caspar Wistar, as well as to Thomas Jefferson and James Madison. Other letters discuss yellow fever and other diseases, education at William and Mary College, the war, and politics, and one letter refers to Benjamin Franklin's "sticcado" (a musical instrument).
The Trists were intimate friends of Thomas Jefferson. As a representative to the Continental Congress, Jefferson lodged at the home of Mary House, whose daughter Elizabeth Trist took on the role of surrogate mother for Jefferson's daughter. After the death of her own husband, Trist moved to Monticello with her son.
Biographical/Historical note
Catherine Wistar Bache (1770-1820) was the point of connection between two of Philadelphia's most illustrious families of the late eighteenth century. She married Benjamin Franklin’s grandson Dr. William Bache (1773-1820) in November 1797.
Catherine Wistar Bache was born in Philadelphia in 1770, to Richard Wistar and Sarah Wyatt. Her brother was Caspar Wistar (1761-1818, APS 1787), a physician and professor of anatomy at the University of Pennsylvania
In 1797 Catherine married the physician William Bache, son of Richard Bache and Benjamin Franklin’s daughter Sarah “Sally” Franklin. The following year yellow fever struck the city. In part because of fear of the epidemic, which killed William’s brother Benjamin, and also because of the urging of their friend Thomas Jefferson (1743-1826, APS 1780), the couple decided in early 1799 to move from Philadelphia to Albemarle County, Virginia. In 1800, after a stay of several months at Monticello, they moved into their new house in Franklin, Virginia.
When the farm proved inadequate to support the family, they began to experience financial difficulties. As a result, William Bache sought a government appointment from President Jefferson. In 1802 he was appointed to care for sick American seamen in New Orleans. Meanwhile Catherine Wistar Bache and their children moved back to Philadelphia. They were reunited in 1803 when William was appointed Surveyor of the Port of Philadelphia, a position he held until his death in 1820.
Catherine Wistar Bache died in Philadelphia only three months after her husband, in November 1820. The couple had four children, Sarah Bache (1798-1820), Benjamin Franklin Bache (1801-1881), Emma Mary Bache (1803-1813), and Catherine Wistar Bache (1805-1886).
Bache, William, 1773-1820; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790; Hosack, David, 1769-1835; Hosack, Mary Eddy, d. 1824; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826; Jones, Mary Trist; Kemper, Jackson, 1789-1870; Madison, James, 1751-1836; Trist, Elizabeth; William and Mary College; Wistar, Caspar, 1761-1818; Early National Politics; Family Correspondence; Marriage and Family Life; Native America; Philadelphia History; Social Life and Custom; United States--History--War of 1812; United States--Politics and government--1783-1809; War of 1812; Women's History; Yellow fever--Pennsylvania--Philadelphia
- Catharine Wistar Bache Papers, 1788-1822; 114 items
  - to Miss Catharine Wistar., 1788 January 27
  - to Catharine Wistar, 1788 September 14
  - to Catharine Wistar, 1793 June 4
  - to Catharine Wistar, 1793 June 17
  - to Catharine Wistar, 1793 June 23
  - to Catharine Wistar, 1793 July 22
  - to Catharine Wistar., 1793 August 23
  - to Catharine Wistar, 1793 November 14
  - to Catharine Wistar, 1794 August 5
  - to Dr. William Bache., 1794 November 2
  - to Dr. William Bache., 1794 November 8
  - to Dr.William Bache., 1795 May 13
  - to Catharine Wistar, 1795 July 14
  - to Catharine Wistar, 1795 July 30
  - to Dr. Caspar Wistar., 1796 April 23
  - to Caspar Wistar, 1796 June 11
  - to Catharine Wistar, 1796 July 21
  - to Catharine Wistar, 1796 July 27
  - to Catharine Wistar, 1796 October 26
  - to Catharine Wistar, 1797 April 3
  - to Hannah Wahn, 1797 July 8
  - Contract (copy), 1797 September
  - to Catharine Wistar, 1797 November 7
  - to Catharine Wistar, 1797 November 20
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1797 December 28
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1798 February 4
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1798 July 13
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1799 November 17
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1800 September 8
  - to William Bache, 1802 November 29
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1803 April 8
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1803 June 27
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1803 August 4
  - to Dr. William Bache, 1803 August 18
  - to Dr. William Bache, 1803 August 27
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1803 September 7
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1804 October 8
  - to Dr. William Bache, 1804 October 22
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1807 April 8
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1807 July 2
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1808 November 30
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1809 June 17
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1809 June 30
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1809 July 5
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1809 July 10; Letter to Bache, discussing plans to visit Philadelphia and a recent visit from Thomas Jefferson.
  - to Catherine Wistar Bache, 1809 September 15
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1809 September 28
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1809 October 17
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, [1809] October 24; Letter describing Trist's visit to Washington, D. C. and investigations into the real name of Mr. Brown. Includes two notes found in the same folder as this letter.
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1810 April 23
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1810 May 29
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1810 June 8
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1810 July 1
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1810 July 17
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1810 August 17
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1810 August 17 (Box Oversize)
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, [1810] September 15
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1810 December 28
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1810 December 29
  - to Catherine Wistar Bache, 1811 February 20
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1811 March 24
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1811 May 7
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1811 July 6
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1811 July 14
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, [1811] October 18
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1812 February 1
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1812 May 3
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1812 June 25
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1812 September 12
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1812 September 28
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1812 November 25
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1813 February 1
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1813 February 17
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1813 July 7
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1813 November 23 (Box Oversize)
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1813 December 13
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1814 August 22
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1814 December 21
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1815 July 12
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1815 November 23
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1816 April 24
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1817 January 17
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1817 June 10
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1817 June 23; Hosack, Mary Eddy Wistar
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1817 July 2
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1817 July 7
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1817 September 12
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1817 September 20
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1817 November 12
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1817 December 31
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1818 January 31
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1818 February 15
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1818 February 18
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1818 October 17
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1818 December 5
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, 1818 December 17
  - to Catherine Wistar Bache, 1820 April 25
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, undated
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, undated
  - to Catharine Wistar, undated
  - to Catharine Wistar, undated
    General note
    January 6
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, undated
    December 20
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, undated
    October 10
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, undated
    May 3
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, undated
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, undated
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, undated
    June 24
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, undated
    May 6
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, undated
    Thursday
  - to Catherine Bache, undated
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, undated
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, undated
    Tuesday
  - to Catharine Wistar Bache, undated
    wednesday noon
  - to "My dear Aunt", undated